Guide to the Mary Ellen Hombs papers, 1971-1986 MS2025
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mary Ellen Hombs papers
1971-1986
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Hombs, Mary Ellen
MS2025
1.5 Linear Feet
Collection contains correspondence, reports, photographs, articles, flyers, and court documents. The material dates from 1971-86. The collection includes material typical of an organization especially one involved with promoting itself and the issues it found most compelling. A good portion of the material in this collection appear to have served as publicity for the work done by the Community for Creative Non-violence (CCNV) including newspaper articles about the group and form letters they wrote that were probably used for mass mailings.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Mary Ellen Hombs donated this collection in 1995.
Historical or Biographical Note
The materials within the collection relate to the work of the Community for Creative Non-Violence (CCNV) of which Mary Ellen Hombs was a member. From the early 1970s to the early 1990s, CCNV was a major force in the movement to protect the rights of homeless people in Washington D.C. Currently, the CCNV runs a homeless shelter in the city and is very involved in providing food, shelter, and educational opportunities for the poor and homeless in the city.
In a 1981 Washington Post article Mary Ellen Hombs stated her goal as a member of CCVN as wanting to "... persuade the churches and the District government to provide shelters in every area of the city, shelters attractive enough 'so that even the most isolated, the most hardened person could feel the desire to come out of the cold". These records give researchers a detailed introduction to CCNV actions especially the non-violent social protest tactics specifically hunger strikes, marches, and sit-ins used by CCNV to present their message to the public.
Founded in the early 1970s by Father Ed Guinan and a group of George Washington University students, CCNV was an activist organization opposed to the Vietnam War. As the war ended, the group began focusing its efforts on the needs of the poor and homeless in the D.C. community. Specifically in 1972, CCNV opened a drop-in center that served meals to homeless people. CCNV quickly followed this meal service with a free medical clinic, a hospitality house for people awaiting trial, and eventually an overnight shelter.
By 1976, CCNV had taken on the dual role of providing shelter for the homeless and making the Washington homeless more visible. They became well known for acts of civil disobedience meant to draw attention to the issue of homelessness in Washington, D.C. For example, in 1981, CCNV erected a tent village in Lafayette Park that they named Reaganville. The tents were meant to symbolize the plight of the homeless in the city. CCNV also erected a symbolic graveyard with 45 white crosses for each of the 45 street people who had died in Washington in the previous five years. Mitch Snyder is perhaps the most well known member of CCNV. His acts of civil disobedience, including several high profile hunger strikes, garnered him lots of publicity. He was the subject of a television movie in 1986 staring Martin Sheen. After his death in 1990, the Community for Creative Non-Violence held less protests and focused more on the running of its shelter. The current CCNV mission is "... to ensure that the rights of the homeless and poor are not infringed upon and that every person has access to life's basic essentials-food, shelter, clothing and medical care." Today CCNV provides shelter, food, clothing, medical care, and educational support for up to 2,500 people per day in Washington D.C.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains correspondence, reports, photographs, articles, flyers, and court documents. The material dates from 1971-86. The collection includes material typical of an organization especially one involved with promoting itself and the issues it found most compelling. A good portion of the material in this collection appear to have served as publicity for the work done by the Community for Creative Non-violence (CCNV) including newspaper articles about the group and form letters they wrote that were probably used for mass mailings. The material relates to specific topics that provide a look at the type of issues important to the organizations including those dealing with food and its procurement for the shelter and also the condition of the different shelters in the city. The people most closely associated with CCNV is Mitch Snyder and Carol Fennelly.
Collection Organization
Organized into nine series: Conference, Correspondence, Court cases, Ephemera, Graphics, Publications, Publicity, Speeches and statements, and Subjects.
Shelters for the homeless; Homeless persons; Social reformers; Washington (D.C.); Photographs; Community for Creative Non-violence (Washington, D.C.); Hombs, Mary Ellen; Snyder, Mitch
- Conference, 1983-1986; MS2025 Series 1; 0.25 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Material in this series relates to several conferences about homelessness and poverty. One of the conferences was held at The George Washington University. The material in this series covers the dates 1983-86.
  - George Washington University Conference on Homelessness, Nowhere To Go, 1986 December 13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - National Association of Social Workers Professional Symposium, Celebrating the Future, 1983 November 19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Santa Clara Conference on The Bishops' Pastoral Letter on Catholic Social Teaching and the U.S. Economy Diana Pearce presented the paper Changing Poverty: Comments on Women and Minorities in the Bishops' Letter, 1985 January (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - APA Annual Convention Symposium, Homelessness: Is it a mental problem?, Mitch Snyder was a discussant, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1976-1986; MS2025 Series 2; 0.25 Linear feet
  The correspondence in this series is divided between those sent to CCNV and those sent by CCNV. The letters sent by CCNV are often form letters probably meant to inform potential donors and volunteers of CCNV's latest efforts on behalf of the homeless. The dates covered in this series are 1976-86.
  - To CCNV, 1977-1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - From CCNV, 1976-1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Court cases, 1982-1983; MS2025 Series 3; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains two court cases including an unlawful entry case brought by the United States against Mary Ellen Hombs, Mitch Snyder, and Harold Moss, all CCNV members, and a separate case against Barry J. Todd. The material covers the years 1982-83.
  - Mitchell Snyder, Harold Moss, and Mary Ellen Hombs v. United States. regarding unlawful entry arrest, 1982 October (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - United States v. Barry J. Todd September, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Ephemera, undated; MS2025 Series 4; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series includes a small yellow cloth bag with the statement "Strictly for Da Boids" on the front and "Hee Hee Hee" on the back.
  - Small yellow cloth bag with the words, Strictly for Da Boids, on the front and, Hee Hee Hee, on the back., undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Graphics, 1984-1986; MS2025 Series 5; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series consists of two photograph albums. The material covers the dates 1984-86. One album has images related to several different protests including marches and rallies. The other album specifically documents the condition of the Federal City Shelter prior to renovation, the protest march organized when President Reagan did not follow through with his pledged renovation plans, and finally images of start of the renovation including architectural drawings.
  - Photograph album: images of protests, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photograph album: images of protests, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photograph album: D.C. Shelter existing conditions, protest, demolition, and renovation, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Publications, 1971-1986; MS2025 Series 6; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series is divided by type of publication and includes the book "Homelessness in America: A Forced March to Nowhere written by Mary Ellen Hombs and Mitch Snyder, magazines, newsletters, and newspaper articles. The newspaper articles relay useful information about the actions taken directly by CCNV. This material covers the years 1971-86.
  - Homelessness in America: A Forced March to Nowhere by Mary Ellen Hombs and Mitch Snyder 1982, Advertising for the book (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Homelessness in America: A Forced March to Nowhere by Mary Ellen Hombs and Mitch Snyder 1982, Copyright application, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Homelessness in America: A Forced March to Nowhere by Mary Ellen Hombs and Mitch Snyder 1982, Edited introduction written by Daniel Berrigan. Edited by Mark (no last name given) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Homelessness in America: A Forced March to Nowhere by Mary Ellen Hombs and Mitch Snyder 1982, Publisher rejection letters (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Homelessness in America: A Forced March to Nowhere by Mary Ellen Hombs and Mitch Snyder 1982, Reviews (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - General Publications, Information: from the National Trust for Historic Preservation: Rehabilitating Residential Hotels, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - General Publications, Jobswatch produced by the Center for National Policy Review, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - General Publications, Safety Network, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Magazine articles, 1981-1986 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Magazine articles by Mary Ellen Hombs and Mitch Snyder, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Magazine articles, Mental health articles gathered for research by Mary Ellen Hombs, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Magazine articles, Sojourners, 1977 April (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Magazine articles, Village Voice Body Count (HUD), 1985 December 03 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Newsletters, Various organizations, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Newspapers Articles, 1971-1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Publicity, 1976-1983; MS2025 Series 7; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains the brochures, leaflets, press releases, and public service announcements produced by CCNV and used to spread their message about advocacy for the homeless. The material covers the dates 1976-83.
  - Publicity, Brochures CCNV, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Publicity, Leaflets, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Publicity, Press releases, 1976-1983 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Publicity, Public Service Announcement, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Speeches and statements, 1982-1986; MS2025 Series 8; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series includes speeches and statements by CCNV members Lin, Mary Ellen Hombs, and by Robert M. Hays, Counsel, National Coalition for the Homeless. In addition, series nine, has a file for oral testimony given by CCNV members to the House District Committee, September 30, 1980. The material within this series dates from 1982-86.
  - Speeches and Statements, Robert M. Hays remarks before the National Conference on Social Welfare Boston, MA, 1982 April 29 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Speeches and Statements, Robert M. Hays, Counsel, National Coalition for the Homeless statement about Anacostia, 1986 April 30 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Speeches and Statements, Mary Ellen Hombs comments Lancaster, PA, 1985 May (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Speeches and Statements, Lin's testimony on the budget, 1985 June (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Speeches and Statements, The People's State of the Union Address n.d. and no author, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Subjects, 1976-1985; MS2025 Series 9; 0.6 Linear feet
  This series includes documents related to many different issues addressed by CCNV during their work for the homeless in Washington D.C. The dates cover 1976-85. The topics include among others salvaged food, deinstitutionalization, housing information for the CCNV property at 1361 Fairmont St., and information about various shelters in Washington, D.C.
  - Attorneys CCNV worked with, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Tim Bass, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Columbia Heights Community Ownership, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Community Development (Community Liberation) meeting agenda, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - CCNV grievances against Metropolitan Police Dept., undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - CCNV meeting about Dale, a member, agenda, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - CCNV errands and expenditures for shelter, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - CCNV shelter suggestions to DHR, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - CCNV story rights, disposition of $50,000 payment for rights to CCNV story, 1985 April 16 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Cities Program CCNV participated, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Documentary Let Them Eat Cheese transcript, 1983 September 07 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Deinstitutionalization information Back Wards to Back Streets PBS documentary, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Endorsements, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Euclid Food Club, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Food assistance Federal level, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Food cheese processing, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Food community services USDA, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Food for the hungry, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Food Salvaged Food: Background and Analysis by Elizabeth R. Withnell, 1982 January 25 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Fundraiser benefit auction, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Homelessness information Frequently used Originals and How to Document Hunger in Your Community Spring, 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Homeless project proposal 425 Second Street N.W., 1985 August 27 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Installation of Archbishop Hickey, 1980 August 10 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Lease information for 1361 Fairmont St. NW, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - National Housing Law Project H.R., 1985 March 01 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Oral Testimony CCNV members before the House District Committee, 1980 September 30 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Philadelphia Housing information packet, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Personal, address book, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Personal, Mary Ellen Hombs car accident, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Personal, Mark Lee car accident, 1978 December 27 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Protest, anti-capital punishment action, 1977 April 07 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Protest, apple pie protest, 1982 July (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Protest, war resistance and tax day, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Public Welfare in New Hampshire, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Religious topics, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Shelters list of shelters in the city, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Shelter proposed changes to the Hartford St. Family Shelter, 1980 June (Box 3, Folder 29)
    General note
    2850 Hartford St. SE
  - Shelter Women's Shelter 456 C. St., 1979 June (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Shelter Women's Shelter 612 M. St., 1979 (Box 3, Folder 31)